so does anyone have any ideas to start
off the
discussion well in previous
talks um we looked into the middle way and we
um we looked into the middle way and we
established that the middle way is the
noble AAL
path and we also said that with the
acquisition position of Y Manara that
comes to be the arising of the no
path so I wonder if we can take up the
question what is your Manara and how
does one put that into
practice are are people interested in
looking into
this could
do so what's the most uh
fundamental directive that you can
give regarding that regarding
youris well perhaps you could start out
by saying
that you know the meaning of
Y we could say you know attending from
the origin or from the source or through
the source even um as a starting point
and I find it practically useful to
approach
it in terms of the direction of one's
attention so ordinarily one's attention
is
directed to objects in front of
you um where things are colorful Vivid
tasty Opa and so on that is where
there's the domain of sensual
the domain of sensual
pleasure
defined sorry
defined you know they are defined also
uhuh the
objects clear yeah well exactly um but
but what that but in order to see where
the domain begins and ends I find it
useful to think in terms of a direction
of attention now Yara is can be
described as attending in the opposite
way um so everything in that direction stays
um so everything in that direction stays
but everything which is revealed there
is Possible only because there is
something else which doesn't partake of
that directionality but which needs to
be there in order for all those other
things to
be so something which needs to be
discerned yes sure you can't directly
attend to it
no you can only discern it
yes and as well something that will
never just appear by itself like it's
it's never magically going to pop out of
nowhere based on watching things uhuh
yes so you're saying that if someone
thinks that by getting absorbed into an
object there or by focusing on something
there that is not how this Source or
origin of attention is going to be
disclosed yeah that's impossible yeah so
so because you might think that
um you know certainly people feel that
absorption practices reveal something in the end
practices reveal something in the end
like there is something that you get to
see what you didn't see before doesn't
matter how you define it might be some
special perceptions of what people think
impermanence is like flux is a common
common example um um where you might get
Visions about your body
like extraordinary visions that say
things that that you never perceived
before but the point is that even if
those things come up they won't be on
the level of that origin like they're
they're still going to be uh on the same
level that you started from which was
absorption into the object so like it's
like um if there are two
paths and they're leading in different
directions you can't take the left path
and magically end up in the same place
where the right path is taking you yes
so so like you can't through focusing on
objects eventually find or recognize the
basis for any experience that you might
have including that whole practice of
wanting to become absorbed in objects
yeah so it it can it can basically only
take you further in that direction and
then once you kind of
um like once you reach a certain limit
let's say that's beyond what you're used
to that's going to feel
special that's that's all it is but it's
it's still on the level of of content
still on the level of experiences so if
you just keep doing that for 30 years
eventually it's not going to be
extraordinary anymore and you'll need
more and you'll need more so because
there's no end to that um further
investigation of of content basically
yeah so that's without satiation so to
speak now what is the other thing that
is fundamentally without
satiation desire well yeah for sensual
Pleasures that's just going to be
endless so you know if you take a more
let's say general or even
phenomenological Outlook and we are
discussing the direct ality of attention
then all those meditation practices that
are concerned with focusing on something
staying with something in front of you
all of that is essentially meditation
with sensuality even if the object
itself might not be seen as particularly
sensual it partakes of that same
directionality and that is not how
you're are going to see that desire for
sensuality is the original suffering you
need to have a reference point that is
outside of that dire of attention which
is precisely the origin that we are now
discussing yeah and and also the issue
with that
is um there's there's also the inherent
dissatisfaction like we were just saying
it's kind of
like it's on the level of getting
something better than what you had but
it's not
like better than what you have within
the same way of existing so to say so
it's not actually trans forming the way
that you regard your experience it's
more like within the same seeking of
pleasure you find some a pleasure that's
more special than the others but it's
not you that's why exactly it's it
wouldn't by most people it wouldn't be
seen as mutually exclusive to have the
pleasure of sensuality and the pleasure
of meditation at the same time it would
be seen as kind of compatible even
because they're not really it's not
really the direction of renunciation
which is the direction that can only be
achieved through recognizing that that
origin and furthermore that
and furthermore that
recognition for someone who has been
used to the to living dependent on
objects it should probably feel more not
necessarily painful but um it will bring
us certain amount of dissonance to their
experience because it's not it's kind of
destabilizing the mode of being that
they're used to so like you can you can
tell yourself if this is a type of
meditation that people who are used to
proliferation in the very mundane sense
can easily succeed with and get good
results and it's just kind of like it
just it just works just like that then
you can see that it's not really it
didn't force them to actually change
their mental framework so to say it just
took place within the same thing so so
that um that's one way that you
can um characterize or
describe what that or say or talk about
one of the consequences of having
discerned that origin is that it forces
you to change the way you live basically
it can't just remain abstract that can't
just kind of let you keep going in the
same direction it has to um affect the
fundamental change in in your in your
attitude basically that's
basically that's
right it brings about the
reevaluation basically of everything
that that you are used to where you used
to go for your pleasure how you used to
avoid pain um that whole domain is now
in realf against something else which is
that origin which has now been discerned
yeah but perhaps we we should clear up
that it is not a matter of just seeing
this once and then all of that framework
is going to flip around and and things
are done um um it this is something that
um one you see this is something that
needs to work on but it is not that that
origin or Source itself is in need of
development because it's Upstream of all
that but what needs to happen is that
one needs to get into the habit of
attending from that origin to one's
experience so to speak um and uh you see
the difficulty then is that from the
point you see in that direction there's
not that much going on compared to that
other direction so the more one this
this right to speak speak about the
discernment so it is in reference to
that origin that the pool of the senses
becomes almost tangible you feel that
you are pulled away or that you are
falling from that yeah whereas before
that it was just like it's it's just
natural you don't even feel the pull
because you're already already there
you're already flying yes so it is like
as if somebody is floating on a river
and as long as you flowing along with
the river it might be more comfortable
or less comfortable but that but you
will not be able to discern is is the
force of that River the current and now
suppose there's a bridge there with a
strong post or pillar in the middle of
that River and you decide to hold on to
that post or pillar when you do that you
don't need to go against you just need
to hold on to that poster only then for
the first time do you actually feel the
force that was that was P that was
pulling with dragging you along so one
way in which one can practically um say
that that that one is practicing
attending from the origin wiely is that
in a sense that pool of the senses
becomes um much more noticeable in one's
um much more noticeable in one's
experience and it is in relation to that
that one's mind then begins to develop
which raises the question if that pool
if you now feel that
pool then what do you do then then
what's next because it's nice to discern
that origin but practically speaking if
you want to let's say stay
there then there need to be a number of
other things in place if this is
practically going to going to going to
have right result so to speak so perhaps
we can go into that like how how is now
one practically going to go about it
like like how are you not going to
overlook that which already doesn't
appear in front of you and that also
like as you said preventing yourself
from going with a poll so that gives us
a chance to explain
explain or illustrate what that origin
actually would be because from where we
said now it sounds like an abstract
notion yeah so um yeah so let's say
there is a
pull towards cality the most common way
so like how would you go about
Discerning the origin and preventing
yourself from falling into the natural
habit which
is doing something on account of that naturality
well like you said first step is do not
do something on account of that pool so
but is that a matter of choice yes
restrain well at least restraining on
the bodily and verbal level that is a
choice which is a prerequisite for any of
which is a prerequisite for any of
this so can you would you be able to not
act by body and
speech if
you just colloquially speaking lose your
mindfulness if you just forget and and
go back to the status quo would would
you be able to keep to to not act even
in the basic U bodily sense unless you
have a sense of
recognition of something else that's
about to your experience such as your
value of
restraint yeah exactly that's what I was
going to say is that even taking on
restraint would kind of point you
towards this direction so to say yeah so
so like to the extent that a person
wouldn't do things like even
with you know
without the help of the dhama let's say
a person has some kind of Ideal some
kind kind of um overarching principle to
the life based on which they prevent
themselves from um committing certain
actions when when they have you know
sensual sensual desires arising that
would require a degree of Y so it could
be like following the Ten Commandments
or something whatever it might be it
it's obviously a little and it's not
enough for Liberation in the in the
Buddhist sense but anybody who doesn't
act out of sensuality has more a little
bit more
y than the one who does because that's
what you are kind of your whole
experience is pointing towards like you
said it's like a river and if there's
nothing if there's truly nothing holding
you back or if you're not holding
yourself back there's there's simply no
way that you won't float along with it
MH um
so
yeah so that's a that's to clear up what
that origin is it's not a because when
you say well it's not an it's not an
object that can be turned into an object
as well so it's more like anything that
in a practical sense at least for for
people to get started it would
be just a recognition in the most Broad
in the broadest sense that prevents you
from acting
out that's already you
God but does that
mean like so as you said there are other
things that have to be in place there so
it's not like doing it once because like
a person okay you have the desire rising
and then I recognize I shouldn't be
acting out of this that's that thought
there is comparatively speaking more y
than the person who didn't think I
should have acted out of this mhm but
but then it's not a matter of just
having that there once because obviously
the pressure is still there mhm so what
what should a person do
then yeah but you see perhaps one step
back still um like it seems to me that
it would be possible for someone to to
take on some basic restraint and to and
to recognize that it is in their welfare
to not act out of every random impulse
or appetite the devices in their mind
but that still doesn't necessarily
disclose the origin it is possible that
somebody has some so we might say that
that is moreon so which I think is
correct but still they might be
completely oblivious to the fact that
there is a further discernment possible
which which which changes the whole
overall Outlook so so it is not that
that mere restraint is in and of itself
going to review that origin of attention
well it it it's not that it's the thing
is like not necessarily that it has to
be revealed but just um just to kind of
give an idea of what it is basically
it's just
that counter choice you could call it
that not to act out is a form
of context that's preventing you from
engaging with the with the content so
it's that's right the person will not re
recognize the principle of what they're
even doing which is why they wouldn't be
able to further that yeah exactly this
is what I was trying to get so if one
wants to
deliberately develop yika in the way we
discussed earlier not that that origin
is in need of development but one needs
to develop oneself in relation to that
origin so to speak that's possible only
if one has recognized that principle
otherwise it will just be a matter of
restraint which is better than than not
being restraint but but the restraint
itself is going to be far more powerful
if it's practiced against an
understanding of that origin yeah yeah
right and so so like yeah so how could
you how could
you well yeah we could we could approach
it that way how could you refine it so
that it's no longer just a
choice a coar choice to to not do
something which pretty much anyone can
do for different motivations even yeah
you can postpone the pleasure because
you want more pleasure later so how
would someone turn it into
[Music] um into like development of this
um into like development of this
principle that would for example lead to
the abandonment the actual abandonment
of the unome mental States for
example well one thing someone could do
is question them
themselves um about the nature of the
sensual Pleasures that are in the
opposite direction of attending from the
origin so one is subjected to unpleasant
feeling or to the possibility of
unpleasant feeling and if the only thing
one knows is to put pleasurable sense
sense experience over against it which
is the only thing the ordinary person
knows how to do in relation to the basic
d
then it's like one steps into the
direction to gain pleasure in order to
deal with the pain which is in that same
direction and so something painful
happens there and then I only show is oh
I want to have pleasure over there that
should overrule or overpower the pain
but what is not understood is that as
long as one steps away from that origin
into that domain there wanting pleasure
regard regardless of how refined and
intense the prospect of that pleasure is
by falling away from that origin you
make yourself liable to that Dua so so
how this is so how is this going to
practically then be discerned more
closely and practice is by seeing that
that whole domain whether it is pleasure
or pain that is on over that is what one
can abandon from the point of view of
attending from that origin yeah so so
like the the pain that is involved in
essential desire is to be recognized at
that origin exactly so so then yeah so
if you don't see that all you're seeing
is the offer of pleasure but right there
kind of kind of like the foundation of
your whole engagement is this pain and
then on top of that you're walking on
top of all of that getting all this
pleasure but the foundation is still the
same so you could say that's that's a
form of an analogy for what that is it's
like the foundation for everything else
in your experience that's happening so
um yeah so you would you like that's
another another good point if you if you
expect to find the pain of
sensuality on the same level as the
objects are you expect to see some kind
of um direct
confirmation observable palp
confirmation that this thing is not
painful that this thing is that this
thing is suffering you won't find it
there because it's found at the place of
that origin so like a subba practice for
example mm could be very easily
done on the level of that um what like
looking at more objects to like
unpleasant objects to prove yourself
that the pleasant objects are not worth
it so you're still operating on the same
level yeah it's to to be seen on that
Foundation mhm for for you to see that
whether the objects are Pleasant or
not this Foundation remains so you
actually you basically you don't get rid
of the objects but it ceases to
matter what they are like and that's
that that's when it doesn't depend on
you having to manage basically having to
cuz all we're saying like if a person
still tries to do it on level of objects
it can be turned into the same thing
like okay sensuality is painful
sensuality is suffering but if it's not
seen as as basically as a background to
the pleasure but it's it's attempted to
be seen
as um a foreground again then it won't
really work it's it might kind of to
some extent give
you motivation
to not apt out but as as soon as the
motivation to kind of apply that that uh
observation onto the foreground runs out
then you're back onto the the the
pleasure because it it basically
depended on like manipulating mhm the
The Experience
so so that leads us to kind of what I
was going to ask me for so what what
would a person what would be a very
practical way for a person not to fall
into denying
of the contents like trying to see the
suffering trying to see the
impermanence um on that kind of
management level mhm so that it's it's
um that perception sets in at the right
level sorry which which perception the
perception of suff that sensuality of
suffering that uh these things are not
satisfactory that they lead to harm mhm
they're un beneficial what would a
person have to do for for that to be
applied on the right level not on the
level of the
objects like what what is it that makes
you not apply it on the right level
let's say that
way mhm so are you asking what makes someone
mhm so are you asking what makes someone
fall away from that question or not find
it in the first place let's say or or
not find it in the first place
uhhuh like they're they're pre occupied
with a certain goal uhhuh that
automatically means that they will be
whatever they do won't be at the level
of the origin
right well what needs to be understood
is that that origin is um more
fundamental than your self or is that a
bit of a jump yeah yeah so because a
person might like at that at that point
if this is not abandoned anything that a
person is thinking about on the level of
sense of self is still going to be
management I see okay so we have one
step back maybe
back maybe
to consider or think whether what you're
aiming towards mhm how what it is out there so
towards mhm how what it is out there so
to say kind of relating to what he was
saying before is that this
uh um level of thing already there of
this what you call it fundamental
mhm is not something you have to create
or
find so to say out but why why would you
be trying to create something because
because you think what's here is not uh
optimal to use that word and why why is
it why is it not optimal well because
it's felt in a way which I don't like
right so basically it's because you want
to get rid of the
displeasure so doesn't matter what way a
person is thinking about it they might
have the most accurate understanding of
that origin but if that motivation
behind them trying to discern it I see
is still on the level of trying to get
rid of what the objects are doing like
the pressure that this the pleasant
objects are exerting in this case if if
that automatic um Endeavor or or Primal
automatic um Endeavor or or Primal
Endeavor
to um Escape that that displeasure is
not is not uh given up then whatever
they do will just be trying to
manipulate content M and so even if
they're trying to see oh this is
unpleasant in the case of sity this is
ultimately suffering this is
impermanent all of it will be just
another basically object it won't be it
won't be the background to this
because well in order for it to be a
background you need to have two
things so if you're trying to replace
the first thing how can you have the
background like you're just trying to
have one thing in the end mhm you you're
trying to have you don't realize it of
course but in the end you're not trying
to see the pleasure as pain
which requires you to have the pleasure
there you just want to have
pain yes or the other way
yeah well yeah yeah so on the one hand
one needs to leave everything including
the Pleasure and Pain of objects which
is that direction in a sense one needs
to let it be as it is and not interfere
while simultaneously Discerning the
background to it keeping one's
intentions in mind that one is not now
Discerning that origin hoping to bring
about to change in that direction yeah
and and how letting it be what is a more
accurate way of saying
that because a person again you might be
telling yourself I have to let it be I
have to let it be because you don't want
to uhhuh
Sure basically you have to endure the
pressure not resist yeah because if if you you
not resist yeah because if if you you
can't be telling yourself anything I'm
I'm going to let it be I'm going to let
it be but fundamentally the pressure is
is kind of the the thing that's pointing
you to do all of this uhuh so doesn't
matter what you do you might oh I'm
going to I'm going to um this is aison
by itself I'm not going to interfere
with it why because the pressure yeah
why what you mean uhhuh so basically
like a person needs to accept that the
pra the the
origin is for the sake
of the the discernment of the origin
happens when you endure the pressure H
that's kind of the that's how you that's
how you're seeing the background to this
you want to see the background to that
pressure yeah not the background to
something else y
mhm and and a a good example of this
actually is uh the practice of meta so like often
is uh the practice of meta so like often
it's done as a form of trying
to let's say somebody upsets you or
something and you want
to instead of training yourself so that
the pressure of an unpleasant situation
doesn't become ill will mhm you try to
make yourself have affection for the
person so that the situation is not
pressuring anymore mhm so that's not
actually training the mind it's like
saying you you know you have a you have
a you're not used to the
cold but then instead of exposing
yourself to the cold so that it stops
you know giving you all sorts of
whatever hypothermia or something you
just your your response is to go back into
your your response is to go back into
into warmth MH so that's why it's not
actually training the mind so the
training training of the Mind happens
when while having the
pressure you keep the perspective that
prevents you prevents that pressure from
becoming U sensuality desire aversion
and so on
so that's
the yeah that's what makes it be right
just so it's not about replacing the
object exactly because you you want to
like basically train your mind so that
whatever object comes up is not
Disturbed yeah and that's how you build
up strength actually it's not by hiding
from things to kind of wrestle against
or you know exercise basically you need
to expose your body to exercise to build
up strength yeah and the thing is a
person might not be well they might
never have been told that that's the
direction where where development
happens but at the same time they might
not be aware of themselves doing it
because that that impulse to outrun the
pressure is so Primal and so deeply
rooted that you might have even heard
well I shouldn't try to get rid of the
pressure and you're still doing it mhm
so that's why it's requires constant
revision of like we were saying before the
of like we were saying before the
intentions behind your the intention yes
yeah that is also how there going to be
the development of wisdom that that
takes place uh let's say well that is that
place uh let's say well that is that
could be another way of describing what
we were just saying like there there's
there's not going to be any like
fundamental Insight or shift in in one's
whole relationship to the world so to
speak if this is not done rightly
because the Insight is about the things
that pressure you mhm not about
something else like the the insights
usually that come up in meditation for
people it's it's on the basis of like
completely just running away from the
place where the pressure comes it's like
a different world almost yeah and that's
actually you know
fundamentally what matters to person
yeah to be free from pressure yeah yeah
because be not moved by pressure yeah
because that's kind of the human that's
a human world that's what you're going
to encounter when you get up the cushion
and start talking to people is this
pressure you're not going to be encountering you
you're not going to be encountering you
know um particles of of namarupa or
something you're going to be
encountering pressure yes so but you see
nobody actually wants to experience that
pressure of sensuality but the
fundamental um lack of wisdom is that
one casually assumes that by acting out
One releases the pressure and hence free
ones from that pressure so why then is
it so feel why then does it feel so
natural to act out because actually one
doesn't want to have the pressure of
sensual desire and that's why it's
unpleasent and and yeah and that is why
once X out but what is not seen is that
the acting out means that basically your
own mind has become the victim of that
habit and so it become stronger so the
actual way out is to not act out and
learn to strengthen the mind so that it
is no longer pressured by those same
things but the recognition that one was
acting out because one didn't want to
have it in the first place is important
to realize so that it is not like um you
know like why am I doing this well
because actually you did not really want
to have that pressure so so there is but
this is of not understood so it's a
catch jne to sorry it's a catch J to
like the pressure the pressure becomes
stronger because you want to get rid of
the pressure and the pressure becomes
stronger then you want to get get rid of
it more and so on yeah and and it just
keeps going round and round and round
actually making the situation worse and
um that's one another point to make like
if your practice revolves around getting
rid of the
pressure many times what will happen is
that things that actually didn't bother
you before now become bothersome yeah
like you weren't bothered by the sound
of traffic let's say before but now when
like on account of of some kind of
practice that's about running away from
yeah every pressure now this thing is is
is is unsettling and like
your the the requirements for your mind
to be at peace become more and more
strict yeah so that is a that is that is
sort of a sensitivity within the wrong
direction yeah so it becomes it becomes
um so it what I'm saying is it's the
same principle like the more you try to
get run away from pressure the more it's
um it's going to bother you and and
um like with that sort of practice you
can imagine if that is bothering you so
much what will happen when you know you
get you go back to the same intensity of
Life mhm that you had before because you
might have toned it down because your
practice and and you don't experience
the same
um breadth and and and and intensity of
of things anymore but if you were to go
back if you had to abandon your
protected environment then you can
imagine that completely over people
insulting you yeah people you know
treating you badly very powerful um
sight sound smell St touches it's not
going to be manageable for you
so
um so yeah like if a person is clear
about this
that it's about enduring the pressure
then there's like any any practice you
do within that it's going to be right
for that very reason if your if your
endurance of the pressure is correct
whether you're
doing um the four sanas whether you're
doing um meta whether you're doing
auba um to the extent to which you can
endure the pressure is the extent to
which your practice is has the right the
right basis and that's also where you
can start discern what is wholesome what
is UN wholesome
yeah yeah because um many times un
wholesome things can be ways
things can be ways
of what is ordinarily thought of as
wholesome can be rooted in just trying
to get rid of the pressure like being
again like I said now
loving kindness which is the usual um
interpretation of meta it seems
wholesome very wholesome on the surface
but if you ask yourself why am I doing
this is because the pressure that's
there now kind of the starting point
that I had is is I want to get rid of it
which which is the ill will so how can
you practice love and kindness when
you're starting point is that you are
not free from ill will towards your own
experience there a complete
contradiction yeah so so
again so
so that's what would be determining
things as wholesome and un wholesome in
the most ultimate sense
um virtue for example mhm you can take
on a thousand
precepts but if all of it is based on
trying to outrun the pressure that comes
from doubt like if I don't have every single
doubt like if I don't have every single
aspect of my day
um meticulously planned beforehand I'm
going to experience the pressure of
doubt and uncertainty then even though
on the
surface U all these observances are
wholesome they might be very aere or
very aesthetic but if it's done for the
sake of running away from the pressure
then ultimately it can't be
ultimately it can't be
um pushing the Mind toward freedom from craving
have you clarified sufficiently
what and how to practically go about
it or should we say something more about
it
well maybe that's
something worth mentioning or we should
have started maybe with it even that
these are these two factors which are so
crucial for the arising of the Right
View which is the word of another and
right attention attention from the
attention attention from the
source so that's why it's so kind of
important to actually ponder about
it yeah I guess that that's one good
thing to mention um so you could
summarize yon as saying that it's
attention that attention that endures the
that attention that endures the
pressure and so on the basis of that
what you heard the utterance of
another about the nature of that
pressure um why it's unsatisfactory to
um why it's unsatisfactory to
unbeneficial to act out of it why it's
not in your control why it Ares on its
own all of that can become recognized
because now you are
not because acting out of the pressure
means trying to own it automatically so
when you have the utterance of another
of the sutas that are telling you that
um
nothing nothing is nothing can be owned
mhm basically you could summarize the
entire brsh teaching y for as long as
you're acting out of pressure you are at
you're very trying to get rid of the
pressure is saying I am is is implying I
am owning this yeah like that pressure
has something to do with me I need to do
something about it yeah um and so the
acting out um presupposes and further for
out um presupposes and further for
fortifies the view that that pressure
has something to do with me but what
needs to be recognized is that it's
actually the other way around yeah yeah
yeah so so then you might have perfect
knowledge of the
sutas but and and you're applying the
same teaching on the surface you're
applying the the perception of
Anisha but all of it is done because you
want to get rid of the pressure means
all of it is done on the basis of
ownership so it can give rise to the
right view because
it's not um you're not getting to
understand that uh ultimate direction of
relinquishment yeah it's it's all still
being done on the basis of what I want
basically which is to get rid of this
yeah and that is putting yourself first
basically in in your attitude and that
origin of attention which is where
feeling Vena cannot go basically um
seconds basically you're you are still
the origin yeah yeah you are still the
origin whereas
actually the whole point of of
practicing yika is is seeing that your
whole experience including what you take
yourself to be is second from that
origin and so perhaps we we should also
say that um when we are talking about
the source or the origin that there's
absolutely nothing theistic about that
because here in the west you know the
whole history of religious and
philosophical thought centers around the
question you know whether God exists or
not basically so we are not saying that
um God is the source of all values and
that this is what we have to find in our
experience somehow um because you know
it might be easy for people to fall into
into that mistake this is a that that
there's nothing theistic about anything
that we said yeah and and not not not
only in the sense of theistic but also
in just a general mystical sense that
this source is some somehow something
that you can
find safety in and that it's yourself or
something like that it doesn't have to
be an explicit um formulation of it as
okay this is God or something um so yeah
it's important to recognize that it's
it's just a um you could say a
structural principle that whenever
something arises in your experience
there's going to be something else that
is a foundation for it yes it's that
simple so uh if you turn your attention
to that which is the foundation now then
something else will be the foundation
something else will be the source mhm
and then you do the same thing and it
happens again so none of those things
are um there's no such thing as a fixed
Source let's say mhm it all depends on
what are you directing your attention
towards what is your what are you
engaged in right now so because of that
as well um the
like the source as a foundation for the
for what you're attending to but there
would be no Source if there would be no
background if there were nothing that
you were attending to so that means that
that source is also impermanent that it
also um depends
simultaneously on what you're seeing so
we can go for example in the case of of
sensuality we're talking about these
Central object and Central
perceptions yeah that's the foreground
that's the content and you can say well
your body your feeling any of these
things the Buddha talks about you can
see it as the source but if there were
no sensal object there no experience
there right now how could you talk about
something that is the foundation for it
how can you talk about um these other
peripheral phenomena that they have to
discern it would make no sense so that's
why it's not neither of them can can can
be identified with the kind of
ultimate um essence of the experience or
something like that yeah they cannot
stand on their own so these two
directions that we started out with
mutually depend on one another yeah
that's another important thing to
realize and this is then in essence why
when there is going to be the noble
right view the main principle that is
being discerned is with this this yeah
and that is and and this and you know
this twofold attention is the
exemplification which when that is
understood you that will be recognized
on other levels as well and it's not
even necessarily recognized on all
levels but the principle is seen and
this then becomes the the the noble
method of the AAL path contemplating
that principle and
applying whatever it is that you're
attending to there recognizing
simultaneously with it that background
and then reading the sutas can be a
great joy because the Buddha already
basically points out oh then this is the
foreground that has got to be the
background when this is the foreground
that's got to be the background so in a
sense you can just read that and it's
like ahuh and and so that's very helpful
well that's that's what I was saying
just now with the practice of the subba
practice of meta all these things that
are usually that sometimes work sometimes
usually that sometimes work sometimes
don't for people when your discernment
is on those level of that Source um
correctly it can't not
work like it it can't it can't not give
the result that it has to give if it
doesn't it's because you're making a
mistake so um that's the that's the the
the yeah like you said it's it's it's
helpful because
then um there's no way for you
to to um to go astray cuz there is only
one way to go tray which was not
enduring the pressure y so that's why
it's not just uh like the right view as
well it's not just having y because like
I said to some extent anyone can have
that Source or develop it more than
others uh it's it's more like
understanding y
as and
understanding so recogn you could say
recognizing in yourself when you're
enduring the pressure and when you're
trying to get rid of it knowing that
clearly means you will always know what
is wholesome and what is UNH wholesome
what is beneficial what is
unbeneficial and uh that's what how
majima 2 starts it says the ending of of
the influxes is for the one who
knows these two things
and that's the person who can tell
whether what they're reading from the
sutas they're doing it rightly meaning
Yono or wrongly Yono but it's the same instru yeah